in this video I will be demonstrating
how to create an accessible modal dialog
using the html5 dialog tag it uses a
polyfill for browsers that don't support
it yet natively for details on the
polyfill and more information on how
this demo was built please check out the
videos accompanying blog post on user
agent mancom the first browser we're
going to demonstrate is safari using
voiceover which is built into OSX right
now keyboard focus is on the link just
before the button labeled login to our
website which will open the modal win
pressed so let's use the keyboard to
navigate to the button log in to our
website button main two items and now
we'll hit the enter key close this
dialog button web I log in one item in
order to continue please log in to the
application you may have noticed that
when the dialog opened the close button
gained focus also note that the screen
reader said close this dialog button
this tells the screen reader user that
focuses on a button labeled close this
dialog incidentally this label was coded
as an alt attribute for the buttons
image tag you'll also note that the
screen reader reports it as a web
dialogue that's because the button is
inside an HTML dialogue tag voiceover
would also announce this if the modal
was coded as a div tag with its role
attributes at the dialogue in fact
setting the role to dialogue is what the
polyfill does on all dialog tags so
screen readers can report the dialogue
properly to the user
finally you will notice the screen
reader reads out the header and the
description in the dialogue this happens
because the dialogue tag has its Aria
labeled by attribute set to the ID of
the header and as Aria described by
attribute set to the ID of the
description text now let's find out what
happens when we tab past the end of the
dialog username edit text mobile menu do
a password secure
with a cancel button you are confirmed
button you are closed a silent button
you'll notice that when I hit the tab
key after the confirm button focus goes
to the first element in the dialogue
focus never goes to any interactive
element behind the modal for browsers
that support the dialog tag this
automatically happens because it is
native browser behavior however for
browsers that don't the polyfill steps
in and uses focus events to implement
this
if focus goes outside the dialog it
loops back to the first element of the
modal if we are tapping forward of
course if we are tabbing backward using
a shift tab then focus goes to the last
element of the modal and now let's find
out what happens when I close the modal
login to our web site button to items
you'll notice that focus is placed back
to the button that opened it
surprisingly this is not the fault rouse
or behavior even though this is
considered best practice in the wai-aria
documentation it is added by a bit of
code in the polyfill the code is
executed for all browsers including
those with native support for the dialog
tag now let's look at google chrome
using androids built-in screen reader
talkback I am using a Samsung tablet for
this demonstration but the behavior for
this device is more or less the same on
any Android device using this software
I'm going to start by navigating to the
link just before the button that opens
the modal since this device doesn't have
a keyboard talkback users must swipe
left and right to navigate back and
forth within the document list to mine
this example use it by creating
accessible html5 modal dialogues for
desktop and mobile link TT login to our
web site button out of lists double tap
you'll also note that it looks like
focus is not just going to the
interactive elements of the page like
the tab key does on a keyboard enable
device instead talkback so-called
accessibility focus goes to all items on
the page that can be read this is
default behavior for talkback and iOS is
voiceover
screenreader has similar behavior this
can be changed but I will leave that for
a future video
now let's double tap to activate this
button close this dialogue double tap to
activate again you will notice that
focus goes to the close button however
unlike voiceover talkback didn't read
the dialogues heading or the description
it also doesn't mention that you are now
inside a web dialogue this is because
different screen readers don't support
all the Aria attributes equally this is
the reason why you chose close this
dialogue as the alt attribute for the
close button image it tells the user
that they are inside a dialogue even if
a particular screen reader doesn't
support the dialogue role this is a good
example that just like at all aspects of
web development you should use
progressive enhancement to make your
code bulletproof now let's try to swipe
backwards past the close button at the
beginning of the dialogue an accessible
modal dialogue using the html5 dialogue
tag webview you'll notice that focus
doesn't go behind the modal just like
when I was using a desktop screen reader
however this is not because of the focus
events I described earlier the problem
with most if not all mobile screen
readers is that they don't fire focus
and blur events back to the browser when
swiping over the document in order to
code this behavior on mobile developers
must set Aria hidden equals true to all
elements outside of the modal dialog
this may seem a little scary if there's
a lot of interactive elements outside
the dialog I mean who wants to set Aria
hidden attributes on all of those Dom
notes however there is an efficient
algorithm to do this and is in the blog
post that accompanies this video if you
are playing this video on the YouTube
website the link to the post is in the
description below it hope this
demonstration was helpful please feel
free to comment on my youtube page or my
blog user-agent mancom I'd love to hear
your feedback thank you